[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
all right let's begin welcome to the
stoa
everyone i'm peter limberg the steward
of the stoa
this door is a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most
at the nice edge of this very moment uh
khalil unfortunately couldn't make it
today so i'm going to
take over uh mcdo i'm seeing duties
um and today is the the final session
of everyone's favorite bad boy from
wales the sense-making
mensch himself dave snowden he has a
series here called naturalizing sense
making and this is the fourth part
of that series and how today is going to
go
is dave is going to share his thoughts
on um
the theme of today and um and he will
tell us what that is
uh and then that'll be about 30 45
minutes and we'll have a q a
uh how that works through your question
in the chat i'll call on you and mute
yourself ask it to dave if you don't
want to be on youtube
indicate that i'll read your question on
your behalf
so that being said i think i said
everything uh
dave uh how you doing today
okay right um no i'm fine back home now
i mean spent the previous nine days
walking in the lake district i'm now
stuck at home so that's fun i miss
looking at your glorious mug collection
so i'm glad to see that
well you've got it again now or at least
part of it
all right so i'll hand it over to you
okay
so what i want to do today is that there
were a lot of questions coming up in the
previous three sessions so i want to
leave as much as possible for that
um so i just want to complete two things
i want to talk about sense making at
scale
and i want to do that in the context of
different types of data
and i want to finish that off with some
speculation about reversing ashby's law
and the importance of that
so people from an information science
background will know what i'm talking
about and anybody else i'll explain it
when i get to that so
that's kind of like the plan yeah um
so if i can share my screen
all right okay so it allows me to share
it thank you
okay so
um this is uh a cartoon
well sorry jason gets upset when i call
them cartoons
gaping void call them illustrations yeah
i quite like the cartoon world
if you don't know gaping void it's worth
going onto the website you get regular
mailers
um they're very into something called
semiotics
and that's something we're about to run
a major retreat on if you check on the
website
we're looking at the road of semiotics
and aesthetics
in sense making that's a participative
retreat
um and we know from a whole body work
i've already mentioned this
that art is fundamental to human sense
making
art comes before language in human
evolution
it turns out the abstraction of art
allows us to make
novel and unusual connections between
things and that appears to be its
evolutionary advantage
and within the context of that we have
the role of narrative
now this is where i kind of like got
started in complexity theory many years
ago
i was working in knowledge management
and
and this was in ibm's institute for
knowledge management it was kind of like
the then hot um
hot thing and i was taking a
contradictory perspective which is by
now you realize it's very unusual for me
right so
i was arguing against nanaka now if
anybody hasn't come across nanaka
he's a management guru from japan he
created a thing called the seki
framework
socialization externalization
combination internalization
and basically what he was saying is you
could make tacit knowledge explicit
and i and many others said you can't
and i adapted a phrase of pilani which
is we always know more than we can stay
and added to that we will always say
more than we can write down
so that started myself with brasso and
others
into the concept that there's knowledge
which is
um low abstraction low codification
which is kind of like the example i've
used for that is a london
taxi driver in this lecture before it's
deep knowledge
acquired over time through experience
in the other extreme you have the map
and i was using maps most of the last
week in the lake
district maps have conventions they have
symbology they're highly codified
they're highly abstract if you
understand you can use them
um but when i got stuck in the deep mist
on high cap nick i was really grateful
i'd been there before
i had experience as well it's kind of
like a native guide in the map
two very different people but the thing
which links the two together is
narrative
so if somebody with deep expertise wants
to explain what they're doing and you
see this in apprentice models
they tend to tell stories good lecturers
tell stories
it's much easier to understand text if
somebody tells stories about it
so narrative is a transition between
high codification high abstraction
and low codification low abstraction the
expert tells stories once you get enough
stories the stories
can be written down they can be codified
that it can be distributed
if when you're reading a document you
can hear the stories it has more meaning
and as you acquire sufficient stories
and experience
that's one of the ways that you
effectively build tacit knowledge into
the system so that was kind of like the
background
and i still stand by that some of the
work i did with the us army was focused
on what's called narrative enhanced
doctrine
so if you actually link um codified
knowledge in the form of doctrine into
multiple
anecdotal data items you can start to
see your sense patterns and the cost of
codification goes down significantly
so narrative is fundamental
narrative is also more important if we
look at the current political situation
and i want to make a few statements here
because this is kind of like
general to organizational change as well
as the politics
one of the associations we've made is
between what is called a trope in
narrative theory
a strange attractor in complexity theory
and an assemblage
if you move into delusion epistemology
so i'm going to run
through those three so
one of the things i hate hate and i'm
sorry you've had susan blackmore and
i've had
a major confrontation with her in the
hay festival on this and the
non-nonsense
she talks about free will i intensely
dislike the concept of memes
um i think it's actually really bad
science
um it was developed by dawkins and the
basic concept is
i mean the selfish gene is an appalling
book anyway marilyn mitchell and others
you know extensively demolished it the
concept that there's something which is
a unit which you seek into its replicate
itself
is like going back to the pre-socratic
philosophers
um i don't know a single geneticist who
takes
dawkins theory talking seriously because
the gene is not the primary unit
and that ignores epigenetics if nothing
else
and the same is problem with the meme
there isn't a single story which is
seeking to replicate itself
what you actually have are multiple
anecdotes which are clustering around
the theme
so in complexity terms they form a
strange attractor
it's not that you've got something which
is seeking to infect and replicate
that's the
magmatic concept what you've got is a
body of narrative that you can't escape
you've been sucked into it and that's a
very different way of thinking about the
problem
uh so this is what the lewis calls as an
assemblage
in that i tell a story you tell a
similar story we like telling stories to
each other gradually
as those stories start to cluster and
form a pattern
um this narrative or the assemblage
exists
independently of the storytellers
and you can see that with for example
some of the narrative structures around
around trump and various other things
what you've got
is an attractor and if you know about
strange attractors in complexity theory
you know the lorenz butterflies the
famous example nothing ever follows the
same pattern but there is a pattern in
the overall sense of movement
and that's what you see in this so a
trope and assemblage of strange
detractor
is a pattern of narrative which is
controlling the way that people think
and it's not simply a matter of changing
one narrative
to change that you've actually got to
change the attractor well or the
attractor pattern
and this is important all right so in
terms of changing attractors there's
various things you can do you can change
constraints
you can create adjacent attractors
and one of the big things that we talk
about is that if you have a really
negative narrative pattern a negative
trope
arguing against it directly makes it
worse not better
what you have to do is to create an
adjacent attractor which can suck energy
away from it
and then gradually shift the system in
the right direction so i want to talk a
little bit about how we do that
and then come into some conclusion
remarks so
i think i did this one last time okay
could somebody just confirm i did show
this last week yeah that's cool okay so
remember the concept here is is big data
which is
algorithmically interpreted contrasted
with thick data which is the
ethnographer
our work focuses on what's called
self-ethnography or distributed
ethnography
so we transfer the power of
interpretation to the research subject
and so the research subject places their
narrative into a quantitative framework
now the best example i've got of that or
the one i normally give it may not be
the best but it's what i normally use
is at some stage in your lives you've
all done an employee satisfaction survey
everybody done a satisfaction survey of
some type
and we got one of these when i was in
ibm
and it basically said one of the
questions was does your manager consult
you
on a regular basis scale of 0 not at
all 10 all the time that's fairly
typical right it's called a hypothesis
based
question so the hypothesis is yeah and
you can see what it is they assume that
managers consulting you is a good thing
so they want more of that
so i found that hr and i was delayed in
the uk i had to wait to talk to somebody
in the u.s i
realized then i was on a watch list i'd
actually run a six-month program which
had experimentally proved that astrology
was more accurate than myers-briggs in
predicting team behavior and hr hadn't
quite forgiven me for that yet so it was
um i was a marked person
it's a good experiment actually i
recommend running it whenever you want
astrology at least doesn't claim to be
objective
um so i got to this woman and i said
okay so how am i meant to answer this
because i've got several managers
and sometimes they consult me and
sometimes they don't and sometimes they
should and sometimes they shouldn't
you're asking a context-specific
question in a
a context-free question in a
context-specific world and remember
that's one of the key things about
complexity
context specificity as opposed to
context-free
i'm not sure she understood me but she
said average your experience over the
year and stopped causing trouble and
slapped the phone down on me
which meant she didn't hear what i said
about her being a hr person in a
research department
and having that attitude we take a
different approach we'll ask a
non-hypothesis
question so one for example we use there
is what story would you tell your best
friend if they would offer a job in your
work group
yeah this is highly context specific and
then we ask people to self-interpret
that question yeah the answer to the
question so they're interpreting the
contextual
answer to a open non-hypothesis question
and they do that for example into six
triangles took a long time to make it
simple
one of the triangles will say in this
story
the manager's behavior was altruistic
assertive
analytical three balanced positive
qualities
now what that actually does and one of
the advantages of having a visiting
chair in a
psychology department is i can use
first-year students as experimental
subjects
and wire them up right they have to sign
up to that when they come into the
department
is what that does is it causes a degree
of cognitive load on the brain
if somebody's answering a series of
light card scales they know what answer
is expected of them and you can see them
just going through it very quickly
what they're doing there is called
autonomic processing
if you actually create a cognitive load
either three positive or three negative
qualities
then they don't know what answer you
expect of them so they have to think
about the problem
and you get a switch into what is called
novelty receptive processing
cardamom calls this thinking fast and
thinking slow
and one of the great ironies is we knew
all about everything that cardamom
discovered
about 10 years before he discovered it
it's just he didn't walk across to his
colleagues in cognitive neuroscience and
ask them some questions
so in cognitive neuroscience it's called
autonomic and novelty receptive
processing
and we don't flip into novelty receptive
processing unless we've really got to
because it consumes a huge amount of
energy
remember i said in the first lecture you
make a decision on the first fit pattern
match
it's low energy cost and evolution
focuses to that
so the cognitive load gets us into the
secondary form of thinking which is
reality in its nature
and so for example if i have six
triangles i get 18 data points
and you can see then how we scale this
because the person who inputs the data
is also interpreting it
so there's no need for an interpretation
by an algorithm
or by a qualitative researcher this is a
quant technique
in what is traditionally a qualitative
domain
and that's important to realize we also
have some interesting ones we've done
10 plus years now work on patient
journey in northern ireland
and one of the scales we got there is
actually a canvas which has
empathy balanced against pain and people
place
markers on it to say this is how i see
it this is how i think the doctor sees
it this is how i think the nurse sees it
and so what we're doing is we're giving
the patient agency
in reporting their own situation and
providing quantitative data of something
which would normally just be a
conversation when a medical profession
came to the bed
and that question of agency is a
critical one we can talk about that
later
i think the other thing this also does
is
it fits into the feminist literature
about epistemic injustice
because what we're doing is we're
transferring the power of interpretation
to the subject
rather than somebody from a different
cultural background
and we've done some pioneering work here
for example in africa in young girls who
mean subject to genetical mutilation and
rape
and we've had those girls acting as
ethnographers
to people at risk of the same horror in
their own communities
and then they can sit down with people
in those communities and show the
results and say what can we do tomorrow
to create more stories like this and
fewer stories like those
this is the whole new theory of change
and i'm going to give you some more
illustrations in a minute
to ask somebody what can we do tomorrow
to create more of these
and fewer of those can engage anybody at
any educational level
and there's no judgment implied in the
question
if you say how can we actually create a
safer patient environment
everybody will say we're doing that on
the other hand if you show actual
stories of patients and nurses
and say what can we do to have more of
these and fewer of those
people can come up with things to do and
they don't take it personally
right so that's called vector theory of
change but the other interesting thing
we did with the guild story is we still
clusters of stories indexed the same way
and we gave them
to experts in female sexual health
in washington the hague and london and
asked them to interpret those stories
the way they thought the girls had
interpreted them
and they interpret them completely
differently so we're now showing two
pictures say this is what they did in
the field this is what you did
now that actually is quite powerful when
you do that with qualitative researchers
because it makes their bias visible
yeah and often they haven't realized it
and there are kind of like three
responses we see to this
the legitimate one is okay we're
different what does that mean
in complexity this is called a gradient
you're an expert
yeah you are bound to see it differently
from the subject so the difference is
interesting
the oh my god we've got to see it like
them well the only way you'll see it
like them is if you grow up in that
community and you get yourself
genetically mutilated then you might see
it like that
the worst reaction then we get this
frequently is they don't understand
their own stories
i'm the expert and you'd be amazed how
frequent that is
now we did a big project with roma in
eastern europe where we used roma
children to act as ethnographers to
romer adults
and when we did the same exercise with
the european union anthropologists in
vienna
that was exactly the reaction we got
they do not understand their own stories
we are the experts
so this is kind of like an interesting
challenge so that's the basic approach
and what it allows us to do and this is
remember i talked about
strange attractors fitness landscapes
tropes
it allows us to map the different
patterns in play
so i can look for example if i've done a
mass capture
you know the blue cluster here might be
males
the green might be females top red might
be children whatever
this is taking the output of
six different triangles and it's a this
is a true fitness landscape so basically
the closer things are if something was
everything was indexed on the in exactly
the same point on all six triangles
there'd just be a big thick dot in the
middle
so this is a distribution pattern based
on indexing so it shows
underlying patterns or belief systems
and when we do this on for example
cultural mapping and this is a
cultural map so in that case i think in
this one we presented cartoons from
gaping boy
people chose the cartoon which most
resonated with their experience
told a story about why and then indexed
it onto a set of triangles
the labels of which came from cultural
anthropology that was kind of like the
research base
and so what you actually got in this
picture is different divisions and
different companies
yeah actually mapped as different
colored blobs
and what that immediately tells you is
that actually this is going to be an
interesting problem you've got some
outliers you've got like red blob at the
top
which overlaps with some of the greens
but it's completely disconnected from
the blue so that's a group of people who
think differently
remember from the first one when i
talked about finding the 17
the people who are seeing something
other people aren't seen this is one of
the ways we do it
and what that actually tells you is that
and
this one is actually not bad because
there are always overlaps
so i can nudge the system around so i
might click on that sort of
purple overlap with green in the middle
and say
okay i need more stories like this and
fewer stories like the ones on the
extreme on the blue
so i can get the system to start to
align
so that's kind of like one illustration
or one example
of the way this works this is a
triangle this is actually one of the
ways where we actually
this is where we're doing journaling um
very valuable process by the way i
started on this
knowledge management you get people to
keep a journal in the software of every
time they make a decision and
from that you produce a map of decision
and information flows
which is the reality of what happens in
organizations
and the contrast between that and the
process map is always extreme
now it's actually one of the ways you
get executives to realize that the
informal networks are making things work
despite the system not because of it
so this is one of the questions when you
made this decision
did you analyze it logically act
intuitively or make a decision based on
principles
three positive values now if you look at
that you can immediately see that this
organization is going to have a real
problem in a crisis
because they're very sort of analytical
or principle based they're not good at
intuitive instinctive decision making
so we can start to see a general pattern
on that
this is another of those landscapes this
comes from work on conflict management
in latin america
so what we did here is we presented a
perspective on the future peace
settlement
um the blue is ex army people
the green is x terrorists and the red is
government
so they've all been presented with
exactly the same statement
and as you can see there's no connection
between green and blue
there is absolutely no point in sitting
them down in a workshop and talking
about things
is given the same data and the same
interpretive framework they see things
radically differently
the one thing you find out when you work
with them is they both hate the people
in red
they regard them as compromises now the
strategy
here which was extremely successful was
we took
the sort of extreme of the blue
and we said how can we make this more
extreme
and the extreme of the green more
so people in the center started to
coalesce
and that was done with more like this
fuel like that
and we do a lot of this on mapping
different attitudes
different beliefs identifying common
areas and it all comes back to this key
complexity principle
of you're dealing with dispositional
states not causal states
so that's kind of like a dispositional
system
um this is another example this is a
public example
um work we did with um pricewaterhouse
looking at attitudes to artificial
intelligence and machine augmentation
um so exactly the same process across
multiple ceos in multiple companies
worldwide
and you can start to start see the
differences which occur between
different countries that's kind of like
a general pattern
yet to tend towards the top right but if
you look at germany and china there are
radical differences between them in
terms of the way it works
so what we're really doing here is
actually
measuring attitudes and that's critical
because attitude's a lead indicators
whereas compliance is a lag indicator
so this is used a lot in safety a lot in
politics and elsewhere
to create a map based on the way people
interpret their own data
and say okay if we want to make sense of
this this is our starting point remember
i said that on day one
in convexity you start journeys with the
sense of direction
you don't try and achieve goals
right so the sense of direction is
effectively a nurse
this is another example this is where we
gather stories about safety in the west
coast manufacturer
and what you now see is the map for each
division
so each division is in a different place
you haven't got an
average for the whole company so the way
you
shift the system assuming the top right
is the desired state
yeah kind of like you know the bottom
right hand picture there
you've already got a lot of people who
are doing the right sort of thing
whereas actually top left you're way
over in one space
so what this allows is intervention at
people's own level of competence to make
a difference
so instead of having an average program
across the whole company
you instead work on different companies
in different divisions
and this draws back to something i've
said a few times
complexity is about the tales of a
pareto distribution
not the center of a normal distribution
yeah it's a fat tail and the problem is
that most
interventions most plans are based on a
normal distribution
and they don't realize the level of
diversity within the system
so this actually allows us to map the
overall position and diversity
and to give an example of this one of
the big projects
we did in south wales is we got children
to act as ethnographers to their
own communities in the valleys so
nobody doesn't respond to a child on a
project
you know the fascinating one by the way
in ohio
which was funded by victoria's secrets
on obesity
i'm still recovering from that right and
we made children and ethnographers
on adult obesity and the children change
their eating habits
yeah and just think about you know if
you make children
investigators of a problem they're more
likely to realize it than if you try and
teach them
either way we've got kids to gather
stories in the valleys
and then we can present to a minister a
government official
the picture for the whole of south
quails but then actually
individual councils or individual
community centers could see the picture
for their people
and that meant the more like this fuel
like that intervention
was taking place to the level where
people could make a difference
rather than sort of big corporate or
government programs as they go down
and that also interestingly means you
get into what are called micro
interventions
and multiple micro interventions are
more successful in nudging a system
than macro interventions and by the way
this is the also the next generation of
behavioral economics
which actually doesn't really nudge it
it yanks
it's manipulative what you do here is
you map and identify when the system is
ready to change
and then small energy input can actually
trigger a change
so you don't start with where you want
to be you start with where you are
and you look at the energy gradients
this is another example
and this is again is from the pwc one
and again you can start to see
differences this is key to
sense making in complexity is
seeing a pattern which is what we evolve
to do as a human species we like
patterns
responding to that pattern and saying
how do we want to change it
another one here um this is looking at
transports
yeah and again you can see an identical
process running different groups and
we're now looking at what's different
what's the same what's similar
as we go through that
all right so i've done that fairly
quickly
right and apologies for that there's
more material which i can
send you what i wanted to do really
there was to talk about this concept
of managing complex patterns in terms of
the way we work
and this concept of data at scale
now the reason i wanted to do that is
that
if you want to actually deal with a
negative trope or a negative concept
let's take my concept of children all
right so we've now
done children's ethnographers in sweden
in wales in singapore in algeria
in egypt and in colombia
and what we're working towards at the
moment is a programme
in which every 16 year old in every
school in the world
can be an ethnographer to their own
community
and capturing stories from that
community about what works and doesn't
work
and the key thing on that is that
actually we're creating an
agency in the local community and we're
introducing a human buffer
into the internet at the moment
the internet isn't effectively an
unbuffered feedback loop
an amber for feedback loops always lead
to perversion
yeah and it's to tyranny of the tyranny
of the herd rather than the wisdom of
the crowds to be honest so that's kind
of like a big ambition on this sort of
stuff
um in patient journey that's
particularly powerful if patients keep
journals and doctors and nurses can look
at those journals
you give the human agency within the
system but you
also in quantitative terms account for
difference
so in one project um you can get
patients with identical
uh chronic this is chronic pulmonary
care
so you can look at patients with
identical physiological condition
but with radically different take-ups in
oxygen so some people just need it some
people don't
we can actually account for about 90
percent of that variation
by the way they interpret their
narrative so we're starting to measure
human motivation in complex decision
making
in terms of the way it works and it
shouldn't take much
for you to see how this can be used
politically
because you're using real anecdotal data
from the field
rather than artificial narrative
centrally
now that leads into this issue about
ashby's law
and this comes back to the origins of
this stuff in counter-terrorism
for those who don't remember ashby ashby
is a famous information scientist
and he said that only variety can match
variety
so as variety of input goes up you have
to increase your variety of response
now if you look what happens with a
terrorist in government the terrorist
actually is doing small things but the
government doesn't know what they are
there are thousands of things they
should pay attention to
so the cost of preventing terrorism goes
out of all proportion
effectively they get pushed up the ashby
line
what we started to do with darpa was and
this is kind of like where we got into
the concept of children
is a government can use its citizens as
sensors
a company can use its citizens as
so the energy cost of processing large
volumes of data
is distributed into a network not into
the center
right so that actually means you start
to gain asymmetric advantage
at the same time you start to stimulate
the terrorists
so you start to throw information at
them
that they have to take account of and
that forces them apache peace curve
and there's a point where you cross over
where you gain strategic advantage
now i remember i was presenting this to
a one of those conferences in maryland
where it takes you about two hours to
get through security to get in
you present it to an audience and they
send you out to the room because you're
not security cleared but they have a
discussion and then they bring you back
in to ask a question
and you know what they were talking now
it's a crazy system i've been through it
many times in my life
and somebody from the back of the hall
said well give me an example of what we
could do to
al-qaeda and i don't know whether you've
ever been in this situation
but um you think of the perfect example
for the
question but the wrong example for the
audience but then you can't get it out
of your mind right so this is american
intelligence people
so i just gave up and went for it and i
said well the next time
sharon comes to washington remember the
israeli prime minister
you arrest him as a war criminal and
there was his stunned silence
over the hall and somebody from the back
of the hall said what do you mean by
that buddy
now for people who know you know this is
it this is a danger sign you know what
you mean by that buddy
i found with americans is a warning sign
right it's like the rattlers tail
uh and i thought oh how how the hell do
i get out of here right the only route i
know to the dulles airport is the lease
retreat from gettysburg maybe it will
work a second time right so i'm thinking
about that
and i said well what would al qaeda do
with them
it would take so much energy to counter
something completely unexpected that
they would have to reveal so much to you
you could do something about it and they
eventually got it
so this question about using networks to
give yourself advantage
because networks have cognitive cultural
diversity within them
that's how you start to rethink things
like ashby's law and attributes
limitations
and human network in human sensing as i
said before is based on patterns
so uh in the first talk i talked
generally about sense making i took five
about five schools of sense making i
then went on to kinevin from that i went
on to apex predator
i've now completed with narrative-based
sense making
um i could have done a lot more than
that all right i mean four four hours
isn't enough
um but i wanted to finish with something
which is eminently practical and
eminently scalable
and i'll come back to this key principle
i want to talk about
in complexity you start journeys you
don't try and achieve goals
well if you're going to start a journey
you need a map of the territory to know
which pathways are possible
and which pathways are impossible and
you need to stop this goal-based
achievement and start
and you know a vector is direction and
speed of travel for intensity of effort
so open to questions
arguments disputes beautiful
um so yeah if you have any questions
start throwing them in the chats
uh i have one cooking up but i wanted to
want to sit on it for a bit so i will
take in andy
uh andy and then these questions could
be about this lecture or all the other
lectures we heard today
or throughout the series so andy you are
um you talked about the value
in both complex and complicated
systems of um
interdisciplinary generalists can you
talk to the
how you value the relative competency
of interdisciplinary generalists in
other words
how do you know
how do you quantify i think it's
difficult i mean i think in the
complicated space you can have genuine
experts you don't need generalists
yeah you do when they come into conflict
but that's a special liminal domain
um complexity which has novel
uncertainty requires journalists now i
think there are two false models on this
one is the neo-journalist concept
which links in with the idea of a
t-shape
right so the t-shape is i'm deep expert
in one area but i know a little bit
about others that's not a generalist
because your own discipline will
dominate yeah
a journalist knows a little bit about
many things and has the ability to
synthesize them
they also know enough to know what they
don't know
so they know when to call in according
to deep specialist
now my own view on this to be honest is
i think
it's something a famous phrase from
kierkegaard nature may deal the cards
but nurture plays them
yeah which which i'm very fond of right
so i think first of all you're gonna
have to have the sort of early childhood
development
which actually creates the right sort of
cortex and other connections
and also the right physical experiences
remember the idea that your brain is
co-located with your consciousness
is actually a very it's called
cartesianism cartesian concepts of the
mind
consciousness is distributed function of
the brain the body it's social
environment it's narrative etc etc
um sorry i'm jumping around too much so
a generalist right if you have the right
upbringing
and you're constantly encountering
different things and you have an
inquisitive household and you argue
about multiple subjects over dinner
and you're not afraid to have
conversations with your friends about
things and you read a lot
you gradually go to be a generalist um
in the school i went to and this was the
norm in welsh grammar schools
we used to do impromptu debating every
week which means you'd walk to the front
of the class and you'd be given a card
and it would say support capital
punishment that was my first one
i hate capital punishment i think people
who supported are evil
um but i had to argue for it without
warning and without preparation for
seven minutes we did that every week
from the age of 11 to 18.
yeah that means you read everything
because you want to
you you never know what you're going to
deal with and that generation and there
are very few generalists left under the
age of 50
in the uk because the educational system
became modular
and specialist and by the time you
your early 20s unless you suffer trauma
the brain is plastic isn't plastic
anymore
um just as a sideline on that by the way
if you want innovation you want young
people to know people that the brain is
plastic up until about 1819 and plastic
again after about 40
50 naturally it's it's synthesis and
integration with older people
and novelty and younger people between
about 25 and 45 forget it you're you're
in the structure of the community you're
in and you're not going to change much
now we do a lot with what's called
transgenerational pairing
yeah put in very young people with older
people so you've got sort of bright
ideas and idealism
coupled with a bit of cynicism and that
knowledge and network
so i think we need desperately need
generalists but we're going to have to
breed them
and try and train them right
remember i talked about acceptation in
the first thing generalists see
acceptive connections naturally
now there are one class of people who
are quite good at it
and they're people who are partially
dyslectic not disabled dyslexic but
partially dyslexic
sorry i i fit into this category so i
know about it all right if the spell
checker doesn't pick it up
i don't get it just don't get it um but
the thing about dyslexia is you're
constantly making connections between
things
you don't see the individual components
you don't build things up in a
structured way
you're seeing connections between
patterns
so there's a very strong correlation
between dyslexia and innovation
the other one which is actually also
really interesting i've worked with two
signal cesiats in my time
um silent series acts are cross wired so
for example they see
text as colors so they literally
can't sit read some writing because it's
it's it's in an ugly color
yeah and those people can also see
connections that other people don't see
and i think where we are now overall on
this is that so-called educational
deficiencies are actually part of
collective intelligence
you need people on the autistic end of
the spectrum you need people who are
dyslectic you need people who have
sinusiac
the system needs that variety within it
sorry you hit me on one of my pet
subjects
um alex
warren you had a question oh cool
yeah super stoked uh
okay so maybe you'll chalk me up as uh
being
in the mode of uh reinventing
organizations having a religious
thesis um so i
uh like a little bit of context as i did
in 18
month uh like business and leadership
training
and then in practice uh we did a bunch
of like interpersonal
looking interpersonal patterns and
reactivity and it's kind of like healing
training a state of being uh and then
that state of being enabled
a group of 40 people we like got in a
fishbowl
and uh there's like three women in the
middle that
channeled a purpose for us around
self-organizing our last retreat and
then that retreat was this magical
experience with a lot of
serendipity and so
my question is uh like
with sensemaker with with this sort of
ability to get like larger amounts of
people like is it possible
like uh like i have this example of 40
people experiencing collective
intelligence
so i'm wondering like what would it be
like for 400 people to have this sort of
sense of self-awareness and and also a
suggestion is like
uh or possibilities i wonder if the
stella could use uh sensemaker and
and like what sort like yeah like how do
you react to that
i think different things i mean once a
year i teach meditation with a buddhist
friend of mine
all right and i come at it from the
point of view of ignatius loyola's
spiritual exercises and she comes at it
from a buddhist perspective
and you know there's an awful lot of
body on the body of religious experience
and the way that people interact in
religious environments
and particularly if you have a very high
degree of
ritual i think one of the big mistakes
the catholic church made was to get rid
of the latin mass and to get the priest
to face the populace
because it lost the ritual and
universality of it
and you know i was strongly in favor of
vatican ii and peace and justice and
liberation theology but i think that was
a mistake
so you can actually change the way that
people think in those environments
the trouble is once you go beyond a
certain level it almost inevitably
becomes a cult
and if if you actually speak to
audiences you know this all right
bigger audiences are much easier to
manipulate than small audiences
yeah i think the proximity causes a
reaction
um so i think and i i think we need to
let the spiritual i mean i think if you
look at the evidence coming out of
evolutionary psychology
uh human beings are religious by
definition
you can't get rid of it if you actually
read richard dawkins and go to his
website
he's created a new religion called
scientism and he's the first prophet he
even has testimonies to people who
became atheists after they heard him
preach all right
so he's following the exact form um and
i think this goes back to the
abstraction
the fact that we evolved in abstractions
means we can't avoid a concept of
something material or other
we're running a program at the moment
you might be interested in where we're
looking at the role of the numinous in
human sense making
yeah that goes back to otto's concept of
the idea of holy so
things like religion and the sense of or
i mean i was in lake district lake
district on the when that sense of war
at 3 000 feet where you can see the
landscape open up before you
yeah there's something about that which
is human right so
we need those elements yeah i think it's
scale
that's where we're working with
sensemaker because what we're trying to
do is to show
differences yeah and show this is this
perspective this is this perspective why
are they different what do you think can
happen
rather than trying to homogenize people
and i think the danger is once you go
above 30 40 50
in a small facilitated group
you tend to get homogenization because
people won't depart from the norm
because they get excluded
so i think it's scale things like sense
maker work but i wanted to go through
that first bit because i think those
sort of experiences are absolutely
critical
and if you don't have them when you're
young you you become
you lose a lot right that sense of
something other than yourself
i mean when i'm with mary boone in
connecticut
um i stay in a house and she
i mean i'm a catholic all right but i go
to a protestant church
and to be quite honest in connecticut
they all go to church but i've
they sing a couple of hymns just for the
sake of it but then the sermon is all
about
palestine or trump or something like
that and then they all sort the politics
out afterwards over tea and coffee
and i think if you go to the catholic
church in ireland you'll see the same
thing
religion centers the community it's not
separate from the community it's about
it
but you did ask me about metaphysics
last time so it was in my mind
all right uh richard you had a question
uh we can't hear you richard
my mike's broken yeah it's you we can
hear you now okay
um zoom was telling me my mic was broken
um this is a very basic question dave my
brain has exploded again listening to
you but
um with the triads when i thought about
using them
um one issue that has sort of comes up
is how does
if somebody's completing them how do
they differentiate
how do you differentiate between
somebody who wants to say
none of the none of these in terms of
the vertices and
somebody who wants to say all of these
but sort of roughly equally
uh there's another applicable button so
you can
say it doesn't apply um
we sometimes actually dismiss stuff in
the center anyway
yeah um in terms of sense making and i
think the thing to remember about
sense making you're looking for a
pattern not precision this is what
people need to understand about
complexity
yeah the pattern matters you
you can't have precision a priori
because the system is constantly
shifting yeah
so whether that so that that's the way
it's done it's it's an n a type function
or you can move triads around and you
can actually link them with dyads and
give relative weight
do you always use positive i mean i know
one of
you try and use things that are sort of
have equal weight um
but all positive we're all negative
examples
all positive are all negative right but
you never have a positive and two
negatives because people then know what
you want
yeah and it's quite interesting i mean
one thing we found
balancing three things gets you better
results than
a simple than say three linear scales
so one things we found on the pw study
for example they'd ask people what was
important in the company yeah and they
had strategic intent
operational effectiveness ability to
disrupt the market and when there were
three lecture scales they were all
scored at 95
when we put them onto a triangle we got
radically different patterns
so we found out what was actually
important to people
thanks thanks richard um
peter you had a question peter s
i think ah which oh peter s that s
okay go ahead peter oh that was you
peter that's the one i was uh with
statistics yeah
we'll take the other peter in a moment i
was i was kind of curious about the
statistical framing
that might be appropriate as you go from
qualitative into quantitative
information is this based in a bayesian
statistics or a frequentist because
frequent as i was hearing like like long
tails
and it made me think okay we're kind of
thinking about the mean
and uh normal distributions
but when people are doing this kind of
self ethnography
does that are they sort of up uh more of
a bayesian kind of updating their
assumptions and probabilities of where
they are
as they interpret their own stories i
don't think they're doing anything
anything remotely that's as
sophisticated all right what they've got
is six triangles and they've got a dot
and they move the dot around on each
triangle to the comfortable with the
relative position
okay so that's what they do okay we also
have
diodes and we have what we call stones
so we have various geometrical
shapes and we're trying to do this on
mass
so one individual results really doesn't
mean anything
yeah you're trying to look for results
over a large number
i normally explain it by talking about a
difference between pareto and gaussian
distributions
um partly because that's you know you
can basically say look you can use
you know the center of a gaussian
distribution is complicated
you've got a common pattern you've got
you've got a many-to-many relationship
but as you move towards the tails of a
pareto distribution you've got a
a few to many relationship and therefore
you've got weak signals you've got
variety
and that's where you do the other name
for this and i prefer logic
is is called adductive research so you
have deductive inductive abductive
yeah so inductive research assumes once
you've got enough data
all the cases of a have b you can assume
a causal relationship
abductive research which is a great
contribution of american philosophy to
logic
is sometimes under the logic of hunches
so what's the most what's the most
logical connection between apparently
unconnected things
and the problem of abduction this is
what poindexter set me to solve is how
do you create objective approaches to
abduction so how is your intuitive leap
more objective than my intuitive leap
and that's where sensemaker comfort came
from
because if i present the same result the
same data to a thousand people and get
them to interpret it
the patterns of the interpretation give
me objectivity
now then within that you can play all
sorts of grains with spearman's
coefficient and things like this so we
do a hell of
statistics with the data but the key
thing is
the primary meaning comes from the way
people interpret the data not from the
narrative
the narrative is in explainums
it's not the primary meaning
did that make sense or did it make it
worse it did a bit
it made a lot better um i was imagining
also sort of an organizational context
that
uh the bosses the executives would want
to have some statistical power to
understand how they were gonna
and that's maybe against the point of of
this
now it's actually very important what i
say is what sensemaker does is it gives
you the objectivity of numbers and the
explanatory power of narrative
but it puts them together all right
and you need them together right other
otherwise it
won't work and it's actually quite
effective at changing executives
um because the numbers drag them in they
pay attention to it but then they read
the stories and they start to understand
what the numbers mean
yeah and that can be really powerful
because they discover it for themselves
rather than you
telling them as a consultant
all right we'll do uh take in your long
lost relative the other
peter s peter snowden with the wrong
spelling yeah
um yeah thank you again for
this session really interesting and
stimulating and
um this follows on quite well from what
you were just saying i think um
i'm i've been involved over the years
and both as an observer from outside and
as uh
inside making things happen in um this
sort of overlap zone between
participatory development projects and
participatory media projects and
one of my impressions enduring
impressions that often the people who
run the project are bringing
agency into a context that isn't
that is going to end up extracting the
value from the agency
and throwing the agency away once you've
left and so i'm interested in what you
said about
just there about um you know changing
executives but i'm also interested
in you know the projects you were
talking about before working with
patient journaling in wales and
i mean what is that that you've found
over the years which
um can help to tip the balance
particularly when you're coming in as
what i i suppose you might call the
junior partner yeah not the person
bringing the money
i think i mean there's several things
all right we did some work around
grenville
yeah which if you don't know was the
tower block which went up in flames and
god knows how many people died
now this to me proved the danger of
facilitating workshops for sense making
because people had workshops they
gathered narrative it was a
participative action research
yeah and i've got a long-standing set of
disagreements with participative action
research because it privileges the
facilitator over those facilitated
yeah and also the facilitator can
influence too much what comes out of it
so there's two things that we work on
first of all when we develop our methods
we did them all in denmark so we could
facilitate in english and people would
speak in danish and we couldn't hear
what they were saying
and we actually remove facilitators from
the process we don't let them engage
yeah because then they're too powerful
and that real and there's a lot of
facilitators who hate that because they
like to be the person who gets the
meaningful story
the second thing is if you make people
ethnographers to their own condition
on a distributed basis over time
you give them an evidence based to argue
their position
because normally they're disabled
because they don't have evidence
they're reliant on the third party
expert coming in what narrative
databases do
is they give them that statistical
evidence to support their arguments
yeah and that's the most sustainable
basis so to me that's really important
and as i said the concept of epidemic
justice is critical to this
um because it's the way that i mean beth
smith who works for me he's got a
wonderful way of phrasing that she says
to if you want to understand epistemic
injustice old wives tell tales
old men are philosophers
yeah which is actually quite a good way
of expressing it all right
and power does it power comes in
interpretation
not in source material yeah and that
that's where you get corruption so
we we push that power of interpretation
right into the community and away from
the expert
and some quality searches absolutely
hate that
so in a way it's not that you have a
magic wand you can wave
at the people in power but that you can
um reflect back the community's own
expertise
to the community in a way that makes it
actionable and usable by the community
not by exactly and also i think it also
means advocacy is taught based into the
method
so if you go to a politician you say
i've got 5000 narratives here collected
from 3 000 constituents self-interpreted
by them and this is the pattern
they pay attention if you go and say
i've done a study and run a workshop and
they don't like the result they just
ignore you
so the and i mean i give an illustration
we did one on um
reasons for leaving the air force in
australia so that they had a large
amount of people to you know take in
early retirement
and that's very expensive so we pulled
in 3 000 stories in a week from
offices and spouses of offices
going to spouses in military
environments is often much better than
going to the military people themselves
right
and the prompting question we had for
that is imagine you're a grandparent
and your grandchild says they want to
join the air force what story will you
tell them
which got lots of stuff right so sit
down
under the bird on the stick in canberra
yeah um
no deference to the americans giving
them an american eagle they call it the
bird on a stick with the implication
they're going to barbecue it right
and we had an absolute correlation yeah
between
poor leadership willingness to leave the
air force and recent implementation of
lean six sigma
now this is not something the head of
the air force wanted to hear
because six sigma was his pet project
um and he'd insisted on having this
question about which major initiative
does this relate to so now he was you
know eating his own words
and he looked at the squadron leader at
the bottom of the table that's kind of
like a
captain in in terms of people not who
are british right
and he said we by which he means you
haven't communicated hour
by which he meant my six sigma policy
properly
this is a classic senior executive they
don't like it it's your bloody fault for
not telling them
go and tell them harder and i remember
saying so we don't know look at the data
yeah you got the screen up there so just
click on it and you can see the story
and remember the question what story
would you tell them if your
grandchildren the first one which comes
out was i'll shoot them first and
they'll be grateful
and he went that's some disgruntled
young officer and i said i don't know
look at the demographics
30-year service female warrant officer
now if you know anything about military
environments you'll know that we now
have absolute silence around the table
this means they've got a real problem
and he clicks on the next one and i
always love this one the title of the
story and the names people give stories
are often more significant than the
story
was why do we have to under the
trees
and it was a new base which had been set
up in a temporary camp on the red desert
and the
bureaucracy of lean six sigma meant they
hadn't got a mobile latrine
so they were having to dig holes in the
desert instead
now that's bad enough in the uk but
things
live in holes in the ground in australia
you would don't want the
unsighted bear skin you know they have
eight of the world's 10 most poisonous
snakes and so on
and he looked at that and he got up from
the table walked to his desk and had a
very quiet conversation with somebody if
you again if you know military quiet
conversations are scary shouting is okay
and i gather over the next hour
helicopters flew in mobile latrines to
the space to the point where they had a
surf it and the staff sergeant sold the
extras on his internal black market so
everybody was happy
but then he came and sat at the table he
said we've taken six sigma too far
yeah now that was numbers and narrative
it's it's what i call see attend act
he paid attention to something because
of the numbers and he acted differently
because of the narrative
thanks great cool
so we're at the hour are you good to
stay 15 20 minutes
over cool so i have a question
um let's see if i can formulate this uh
correctly
that's maybe it's a device too for for
the stowawa
so one of the strange attractors at the
stoa is
i guess i would say authentic dialogue
uh having setting the conditions for
people who strongly disagree with each
other have deep disagreements to have
conversations and so we've been
experimenting with a lot of these
intersubjective
conversations focusing on enabling
constraints of them
um and it's interesting because i'm
dyslexic or mildly dyslexic and i'm
pretty good
at code switching and speaking different
kind of perspectives and using terms and
and whatever and i think this is what
affords me
i think that's what afforded like susan
blackmore to dome chomsky to like you
know
alexander duke and to come in to the
store and feel warm by the the digital
campfire
um and then the code switching i think
it affords two things it like it's like
camouflage like you said it scrambles
the pattern matching
but also uh it's like mimikri in the
sense that it's like
you gesture to the terms of their own
strange attractor
um as it's almost like a trojan horse so
i'm wondering
if if if that's a strategy that works
and someone's not gonna meet someone and
if we could be more sophisticated about
it here in order to like
trojan horse them into our strange
attractor
well as you know i joined so when when
you don't have them at midnight my time
right i'll come on them right um
because it's been enjoyable having the
conversation i think the conversation is
some way more valuable than the
presentation
um if i was in your shoes i would run
fewer sessions and longer ones
yeah there's just such a richness in the
amount you're offering it's impossible
to follow it all and
you end up like this discussion could
probably go on for an hour and it'd be
better for it to go on for an hour than
something else right so i would say that
i'd also look at the tricopticon method
which i think i sent you
which is where you bring three experts
together and then they debate in another
people debate around them
and that's something we developed over
the last five years to handle how do you
get people from different backgrounds to
have different dialogue and not dominate
the group
um so i think that there's other things
like that i would look at
right because if we want to create this
interdisciplinary world
we need disciplines to compete with each
other
okay and um yeah the synthesis then is
quite fascinating is what we've been
doing on retreats the one we're doing on
semiotics and aesthetics
we're bringing together a woman who does
origami and understands the science of
that in the mathematics of it
together with people who are a pure fine
artist together with musicians together
with people who understand the
neuroscience of it and we're throwing
them together in this highly structured
environment over five days
right and i've always been opposed to
things like open space
because open space allows people to walk
away from things they should
pay attention to so we we tend to
orchestrate dances in which people have
personal safety but they're having to
face up or talk with people they
can't walk away from them they have to
listen to that
and then respond
cool thank you um
[Music]
anjan you had a question
hey dave um
i i'm trying to feel for the question
i i'm basically curious where
people just innately quote unquote
common sense
kind of embody complexity thinking um
and where is it kind of lost in
education or
growing up uh
i sometimes call complexity the science
of common sense
yeah and if you haven't heard the
children's party story i'm not going to
perform it now you can look it up online
and there's loads of version of it
all right basically we all manage our
families in our relationships is complex
adaptive systems
now we we we know that we can't predict
the future we can change
if anybody's got teenage children you
know you put a lot of
deep manipulative effort into managing
the dispositional state so they're more
likely to do good things than bad things
but you can't control the outcome all
right
teenagers are good for teaching
complexity so i think it is the way we
it's it is a natural science all right
that's really important to understand
this is not a social
science this is a natural science and
and that's
where i came from the start i think in
education the danger is we get
ideological about this
so for example some of the stuff we know
when i was a kid we had to learn a poem
every week
and we complained like hell about it um
but it actually turns out doing that is
hugely valuable for your cognitive
development
in terms of the way his brain and the
brain is
developing all societies
constrain young people in order that
they can learn and then the constraints
get relaxed
so i think part of the danger is you
know some of the ideas in education are
based on how i would like to be educated
now i'm 40 years old
not what somebody is 10 or 11 or 12
actually needs
in terms of development right um and i
there was a big thing grew up in the 70s
and 80s and probably cognitive for
science has overtaken this but
of the sort of adult development models
and adult maturity models
and those that come across into the
coaching sector intact without
validating the science behind them
and i think any linear hierarchical
model
is actually dangerous
right we we have this love of linear
hierarchical models because
it it actually it privileges the
consultant it privileges the facilitator
it privileges the coach
it is there because they're custodian
the model and they have to take you
through it
yeah and i think that's dangerous i
don't think that i think it's bad
science anyway
so there are aspects of traditional
education which have value
but remember traditional education i
mean we did exams at 16 and 18
and we have plenty of time between it to
think and play and explore ideas
my kids had to do a module like every
six to eight weeks so they got into i've
got to pass the exam in this i'll focus
on this i'll take the box i'll move on
so there was no room for exploration we
used to play in the streets
and you had to learn to live with people
who you didn't like
i mean my children spent all their time
getting bust to safe environments
yeah um so we we
we i think one of the big things in
education is we
you know we used to go and play in the
fields we disappear at 8 00 am in the
morning and come back for dinner
right and that's sort of freedom and
exploration has just been driven out of
society at the moment and i think that's
also part of education
if i could ask the the compliment as a
follow-up um
where does where does common sense and
complexity thinking most
diverge i eat where should you trust
your
common sense um
i think what it depends all right i
think it's it's actually
complexity is difficult for people from
northern europe and north america
it's actually much easier to explain it
in southern europe or asia or africa
and the reason in north america and um
northern europe is the dominance of
social atheism
so there's a famous experiment in
geography of thought which i recommend
you run it ask people what's the odd one
out
of cow chicken and grass
all right so just have a think you've
got cow chicken and grass what is the
odd one out
the dominant northern european north
american is to get rid of grass
because you've got two animals and one
vegetable the dominant southern europe
celtic fringe of
of britain africa asia is to eliminate
chicken because the cow has got a
relationship with grass
yeah and communitarian cultures think in
terms of relationships
whereas atomistic cultures think in
terms of categories
and also northern europe europe and
north america is where the enlightenment
has the biggest impact
and the belief in causality and linear
material causality which comes from
count onwards
and it's very very difficult to break
somebody from those backgrounds into the
concept that some systems are not causal
where if somebody is a taoist it's easy
because they know some things just are
there's no reason for them to be they
might be different next time and i think
that that's where you get the difficulty
i i blame protestantism for this by the
way it says heap of the mischievous grin
and actually i'm right because what
protandism did is it's all about your
individual interpretation of the world
in your individual relationship with god
and to hell with the community
yeah and and that's where it comes from
all right um chris c
you had a question if you're going to
meet yourself
thank you so much dave uh this is just
so rich and i've
i've already joined your life too much
i've been watching your face
yeah i'm having a good time and this
won't be the last time i
watched this session either i'm really
curious about
how we might bring these process
processes of ethnography to our own
communities based on something that you
alluded to earlier
and i'm also curious to know how will is
generated for
folks to actually do those processes
okay so we i mean the thing i run is
called the can having center
yeah this is my retirement job so i can
go and do the work i want to do and let
somebody else handle a commercial site
right
so canarian center runs on a membership
basis
we have academic members not-for-profit
members people like the international
red cross and the like
and they get basically unlimited use of
the software for their membership fees
and we work together we've got programs
going on climate change at the moment on
the numinous
so participate in those right those are
open
um the commercial side will license and
and sell the software to you
right um and there are things like quick
starts and training so that's that's
where the commercial side runs
yeah um but we're really open to things
like with
yeah running that training and setting
up something with the stowe we we'd look
at doing that
right um and my i've got the freedom now
in my research center to do what i want
to do rather than what i need to do to
manage the cash flow so that's where i
am
yeah thank you and can you say a little
bit about the generation of will for
folks to actually follow through with
the journaling exercises and such
well the key thing is to there was an
old rule i created on knowledge
management is never ask somebody to do
something on the basis it will save them
time in the future because they know
you're lying
so what you actually have to do is to
reduce the time now so
if i take some of the examples what we
did with the us army
is we said keep a journal up to date you
don't have to write a patrol report
yeah we got 100 compliance on that
nobody wants to write a patrol report at
the end of the day all right and
actually the real-time data was more
valuable over multiple company
commanders
we've done a lot by using children on
school projects so a school class
gets sent out to do ethnography
yeah that actually satisfies
baccalaureate and other educational
reliance
requirements for community engagement to
understand the statistics so teachers
are behind it so it happens
uh with chanel my favorite client
because they stay in really nice places
chanel is fun right with their top
leadership
group we got them to keep journals
because they were on the leadership
development group therefore we could get
them to do it
uh with new employees we basically say
for your first few months you've got to
keep your journal and every week you'll
be asked to go and interview somebody
and that's how we get knowledge from
senior staff
so the key thing is to think about it as
doing something which has operational
utility to people rather than something
which is yet another survey
the other thing is i mean sometimes we
call this stuff engagement because
if i go to a company when i'm just doing
one with one of the big farmers earlier
on today
right and it was kind of okay so we'll
present your vision of the future of
of you know this is a purpose statement
god help me from purpose statements but
they're prepared to pay me money so i'll
do it all right
so we'll present the purpose statement
to the whole of your staff
we'll get them to tell the negative and
positive story about what the statement
excites
they'll index it and then we'll draw you
a map
now what we're doing is we're engaging
them in assessing the situation not
surveying them
right so we we do mass situational
assessment and micro scenario planning
so basically a ceo can consult the whole
of their staff and get one of those maps
back in 10 minutes
and provided you give feedback to people
to tell you what you do it they're then
part of the part of the solution finding
rather than being subject so that that's
the sort of engagement side of it
thank you very much all right so this
might be the last question i'll read it
on john's behalf
um how did you decide which concepts to
use for the corners of the triangles
uh do you vary them for different
contexts
i mean academics get this one straight
away the subject you're looking at you
do a literature search
yeah and you identify the core concepts
in the literature search and you
construct the trials from that so you
can always authenticate the triangles
back to the
back to knowledge in the field and so
that's how we do it
and we have whole libraries of these
things now yeah that we we should come
from different backgrounds
so it's it's like if you look at
somebody doing longitudinal research
they gather narrative they transcribe it
they tag it in something like nvivo
they have a theory of the field in mind
when they do the tagging
we take the theory of the field we
translate it into triangles but then
people self-tag
so it's not done by the expert yeah so
it creates a grammar of meaning is one
of the ways i phrase it
all right so uh we'll end here
before we do i'll hand it over to dave
for any kind of concluding thoughts that
you haven't uh about the series or
anything you'd like to leave us with
well i've enjoyed it it's been a lot of
fun yeah
um last week was hard because i just
walked you know 18 miles and 4 000
feet but yeah you kept me awake enough
that i survived so that was good news
beautiful uh so i'll make some closing
announcements in a moment but dave
you've been a big influence on my work
uh and my thinking
and i'm very grateful to have you here
at the stoa um people have been reaching
us saying they love this series
and so we'd love to have you uh back
anytime we're always happy to do that
um so that being said uh
next event coming up tonight uh is
called liberating structures
it's some kind of facilitation
techniques where i think they like
tinker around with enabling constraints
of different uh
facilitation methods in order to
engender creativity
uh the the founder keith is coming in
uh that's eight pm eastern time you can
check out uh
our website for um maybe too many events
coming up
uh more will be longer coming so
stay tuned for that uh we have a patreon
you can check out and our sub stack
it's supposed to be still substack that
being said dave
everyone thank you again for coming out
to the store